all right welcome back cohort 4 this is
our second discussion of chapter
10 next week will be our final week
overall so we'll talk about um future
textbook groups give a little time or
people can fill out the forms now for
feedback they can add feedback there's a
lot of other
um pieces that we can talk about but
this will be the last recorded
conversation so nice times let's go to
10 and um does anybody want
to begin with any question or we'll look
at what's already been
written um so so Daniel I
to kind of
General
um since I'm new to this process one one
of the questions that I wish I had asked
you sooner
was it as we uh participate and
contribute
to in this process
um are there certain things that you
would like to
see that the authors would like to see
um so what I'm wondering about like in
terms of
feedback that we can
add uh through time is you know are they
concerned about you know what what
audiences they're trying attempting to
reach um are they concerned about what
principles what concepts might go over
people's heads uh and make them TR away
col difference
prematurely um so that's one question
that's General the second question I
have is um and I put I added a
row in
theoda
um I was thinking that if one of the
objectives of this book is
to have people who don't have the
physics
background walk away thinking I would
like to apply this to the work that I'm
doing and of course this is very selfish
those S very Sly describing myself
um
so if if we don't want to lose
people could there be a document
somewhere and if it exists let me know
where basically have has a list of okay
in order for to understand to fully
understand and I'm just going to say the
free energy Principle as an example in
order to fully understand the free
energy
principle here is a pathway of knowledge
that you need to
complete and it goes in a sequence from
you know concept A to concept n and then
uh you have the concept
the
equations if if the concept comes with
equations and then just very succinctly
described you need to know this and you
need to know this and then links to
videos and resources online so that
basically a person can follow a
self-directed learning
pathway and one of the things I've done
over the past week is just I decided I
want to take a deep dive into the free
energy principal where did it come from
who came up with it how did they use it
do they use it in physics in
engineering
Etc and I found that it's really helpful
so that was my main com word
today thanks okay I'll give uh short
responses to each and then anyone else
can add so what what what with the
authors like par and Pula and friston I
mean they're happy that were enlivening
and and working with the
textbook um we started doing it
obviously like the first day that we
could and we've given them feedback on
little typos and minor things but also
people have engaged with them on more
substantial
topics and
[Music]
um they uh as authors and as the
Publishing Company they're they're at
least open to our
proposals there's no questions in the
textbook um and and that one textbook
isn't the be all and all so it's
definitely I think great to see how we
can serve the authors and also the
broader Niche and um in terms of like
all backgrounds and the generalized
learning curriculum like this textbook
group is low efforts All Things
Considered we don't have to prepare the
materials and especially now having gone
through it multiple times we um just
show up and enjoy but the broader
project of
making knowledge spaces so that people
can have self-guided and have that be
like um across different languages and
Technical backgrounds I mean that's the
educational project that the Institute
is working on so for that we just need
people who are seriously committed to
actually engage in that um at a slightly
smaller
scale Ali I
believe um in the resources
page this list of
[Music]
papers goes from from less formal to
more formal
but this is an infinite regress you're
going to find that you keep on pulling
back to to fundamental concepts which
which may be good
um but yes the textbook group is not the
total
educational Paradigm it's just one
offering and we eagerly look for people
who want to stand up the textbook group
and see what it can be all the lwh
hanging fruit like filling in the
natural language descriptions of the
equations and curating the discourse and
adding more notes and all these things
and then also the reach goals for the
textbook
group um like developing the software
repositories that have the
examples and all these other things and
then even the broader educational goals
that go outside of the textbook
group thank
youate any anyone else have a I thought
on
that yeah
oi yeah so uh I believe being um a
relatively new uh discipline and uh even
a new uh I mean research Niche uh I
don't think active influence has reached
its full uh form yet in terms of being
totally structured uh around a definite
road map and so on so uh it's a bit like
neuroscience at large so we know that uh
unlike many other disciplines such as I
don't know physics or
mathematics uh which have uh a
relatively more structure to uh the
knowledge base they have uh in such
disciplines as Neuroscience or an active
influence or many other um cognitive
science and uh psychological Sciences as
well uh we we don't have this definite
road map road maps yet uh so one way to
approach active inference is um to
somehow uh determine the target topic we
try to uh we try to study using active
influence framework and then try to find
kind of romatic or um multi Branch ways
to uh approach or at least converge onto
that topic so if we expect uh the
learning path of active inference to be
a totally linear and coherent pathway uh
getting us from point A to point B and
Beyond uh I I believe uh we might uh we
might be disappointed at finding out
that there isn't any such uh road map
yet I mean uh obviously in U coming
years there might be more structure to
uh the learning path of active inference
but uh as it's typical for many other
new disciplines and research areas we're
we're still exploring the forests and uh
we don't have uh the cartography of the
whole area yet at our disposal
um thank you yeah that I
make that makes sense um I think so I I
understand that
because
fully
um so I would say that in my previous
conceptual work
uh primarily in evolutionary biology
andology
um and you know the extended uh
evolution of
synthesis I think people would say for
example I want to if I want to apply the
concepts of n construction to my new to
my
field is there a linear time no there is
you know um if I want to include
everything that's under the
extended evolutionary sythesis no
there's no it's completely um it's quite
tough actually to connect with the big
areas that people have work
them but um I think there might be room
somewhere in in the active in Institute
to to start thinking about at least
like the very basic fundamental concepts
so I think that if somebody sat them
down and said I want you to put you know
do this for the extended Evolution syes
I think I could sit down and say if you
don't know these things you're going to
be completely lost in this little CH so
there may be some
foundational aspects to um in this
framework that could be made accessible
so to me it's all about accessibility
because so why am I so concerned with
this um it's because I've been looking
for 20 years for a conceptual
framework that I feel actually
addresses aspects and phenomena that I
have been looking at for this
long um in what I call regenerative
population health the focus in humans
and the active inference framework is
the first framework I have found that
actually I can tell has the potential
for allowing me to talk about things I
could even been needing to talk about
before but things that I can actually be
used
to and um
so in my case since I my ultimately have
a very fly aspect to the this which is
um I work on population Health uh
projects in education and hopefully in
communities there's a certain urgency
that I feel that I I Can't Go For
example into an audience of Public
Health
scientists without being able to say
something about why it's important to
understand
and that's what I'm yeah what I'm
struggling with yeah we we're we're like
making a thousand small tracers with
people's questions here no questions no
tracers a thousand questions a thousand
tracers we can use curation and
attention as well as language models to
synthesize what we already have written
into many of the bases now there's
actually two components what you ask
which is the necessary and sufficient
information
and the sequencing sequencing in
linearization is a separate question
than what are the
fundamentals the fundamentals are what
are covered in this textbook sanj's
textbook the literature those are the
topics that we return to again and again
now they might be challenging which then
beets the question of learner specific
sequencing and context specific
sequencing having the situational
awareness to know what you need to go
into or not when you're conveying active
inference for certain
audience but yes we as part of a broader
educational project outside of just the
textbook group can use the ontology and
other techniques to develop knowledge
systems that that let us address these
questions we're very very recently in
the game and with very very few people
months dedicated to the broader
educational project but if it's
something that people want to
do there's always a niche for people who
want to contribute to active inference
education by doing something that's much
like the textbook group like for cohort
6 or something or by diving back into
the work that people have done over the
years on the broader question like the
fundamentals here that Brock started um
I guess a year ago or the other
education
kind of first takes it's just a big
Journey but again with our knowledge
engineering project and our literature
compilations and all these other
things it's the the challenge that we'll
address yes I there are so many I'm
finding all kinds of resources as you're
talking thank you
appreciate any um thoughts on 10 or or
any
other
questions one Sean you asked about the
computational
complexity as far yes yes I did yeah
yeah as far as I know the best Oli
please correct if we have not a
different information but I believe that
the best information was the
computational complexity right here in
the branching time active
inference paper and model
stream uh the
computational model stream 6.1 branching
time active inference paper here's 21
minutes in and actually the
computational
complexity of of uh active inference is
like it's almost what you'd
expect is it EMP hard problem or it's
just
uh I'm I'm
not able to compare it to NP and sat and
all of that but just at the within the
um computational resources space I mean
it's okay it's the policy Horizon the
time Horizon depth
times um how many policies you have
times how much time times how many
hidden states there
are okay just like how many things do
you have to keep track of broadly and
then branching time active inferences
using her istics to significantly reduce
that complexity but they presented
several complexity
calculations in this
paper and and with empirical run times
yeah
Ali I guess so branching time Act of
inference the attempt was to reduce the
um complexity class of the problems from
uh exponential complexity to linear
complexity uh so that was one way to do
it but uh a much more recent one
actually it was from a few days ago uh
is this recent paper by friston at all
namely supervised structure learning in
which uh they have proposed an
alternative uh way to uh reduce the
constrainted mutual information of
expected free energy
so uh it's again another way to um
reduce the complexity class of the
active inference or um uh probably any
other inference-based problems as well
uh so yeah there are uh some
attempts
uh which um they explicitly address uh
the problem of complexity of um re real
situ real world active in
problems but uh one of the main
criticisms of uh or at least one of the
main drawbacks of uh implementing active
inference models in past years was
exactly uh based on uh the exponential
complexity of
uh of um higher level generative models
and U the
ensuing um I mean uh intractability of
the computation that resulted from
that yeah yes um so yeah so when I look
at the uh generative model and the
optimization problem it seems to me that
It suffers the same uh curse of
dimensionality uh as we uh had in
dynamic programming when you so
basically your time uh explanation
increase in the the number of
states the more number of states whether
it's hidden States or or exp States and
also the number of
policies um that so I wonder what kind
of a trick they have being able to use
to to reduce the
um computational complexity from
exponential uh to um to kind of
polinomial or lar you know linear is a
form of polinomial right so explanation
is much much
faster sorry is much slower than linear
uh I mean near in terms of input you
know so our input are
um in in
in in the
um active inference model minimization
problem the the model needs to use data
uh which are the observations the uh
dimensions of
um of
States uh the amount of
policies yeah there's there's one issue
I wonder if if someone can help me so
the the ACT defines the policy as as the
um the action they take at each time
Point affordance action affordance is
the action you take at each time Point
policy is a sequence of actions for a
given time Horizon
right right so it's a sequence of action
uh at uh at each time
Point um so my understanding of policy
is that they are actually uh they there
are not only a function of time not
there are sequence of time but also
there are sequence of States depends on
what states you're in uh you take uh
different actions not not just the time
but also uh the hiden hidden
States
um so I wonder if they're are the same
um if what are the
same you know so so uh action as a
sequence of Time Versus action as a
sequence of
states and time and know like ideally
whether um you take the action at 2:
p.m. or 7: p.m. or 11:00 p.m. like the
number of the
time policy selection should be
invariant unless the time is the
determinant factor for which policy to
take so the time number itself shouldn't
matter and then as to whether a given
observation or hidden state has a
bearing on policy selection that's the
question there's no reason to address
that question in the abstract because
obviously we can imagine situation that
do and don't have that um and also while
we're in this space of of computational
accelerations like in the in the most
recent message passing live
stream now there's direct policy
inference without expected free
energy so I mean that's why we just hold
on to our hats and stay in the game
because it may not be required to
iterate overall policies with an
expected free energy
compare the expected free energies you
know du research on
EF if you read the paper 56 and watch
the discussions with
Magnus we heavily discuss this direct
policy inference
technique so sometimes the kind of all
by all by all is like the
pedagogical or just the first
sketch
but don't wait on the sideline because
you're worried about a computational
Slowdown that may or may not happen
either jump in and find out about that
slowdown or jump in and then you'll find
out that there's no slowdown or that by
the time that you get to actually
building that model in three months or
six months that the computational
environment has
evolved but the general
yeah so I I'm actually I'm I'm um
supervised my student to build the um
build the active influence
model and when uh when I so so you have
to you have to Define uh the policies
um what is Define State you define the
afford and then the time
Horizon what is the for this those are
the actions that can be taken in a
moment up down left right four
affordances and then we're going to do
you know two time steps and then there's
16 policies the policies are just the
enumeration of all the possible
sequences of affordances of that
length so policy construction is Trivial
policy
evaluation traditionally has been done
with the
efe but
now there's an even more direct way to
do
it doesn't mean that this is the best
way to do it in every single person's
situation for every single problem just
that there is a technique now where you
don't need to do expected free energy
based
comparison you can do generalized free
energy based direct policy
inference it just is that
way yeah
so I'm repeating myself uh sorry just a
one last time hope somebody can help me
so policy is defined as function of time
right so in the sense that you see it's
a sequence of action that's a policy
defined in the
textbook um sequence of action you know
at time one what you do at time two what
you do left or right those actions but
in general in my area in my uh dynamic
programming area the parties are defined
as a function of State not not only time
but also
State uh in our example for example if
whether depends on what whether you're
hungry or not hungry if one of the state
of your
senses uh data is that whether you're
hungry or not then you know your PES
actually depends on whether you're going
to go for food or or just just take a
bite of some food depends on your state
you're the hungry or not hungry State
you know not necessarily depends on time
well yes in different areas of control
terms like policy are used slightly
differently but broadly we're talking
about the same thing which is a policy
is a sequence of actions and you can
construct the model to be borne upon by
hunger or
not so whether or not a given
observation or hidden state has a
bearing on a given policy selection
that's up to the
modeler that's not going to be addressed
by active inference textbook group
generalities but yeah if you make a
model where hunger Bears upon the choice
to eat an apple then you have your
answer if you do it where it doesn't you
also have your
answer okay but there isn't an in
principle answer to a situational
design so so what you're see that as a
as a researcher I can Define the policy
in different way not not uh not just the
sequence of action uh over time by a
sequence of action over over States over
um hidden States for example as part of
constructing the entire generative model
so a b CDE e and so on you're right you
decide not just the affordances and the
time Horizon which Define the policy
space but you also so establish the
sparity and the connections of what else
is
included so if it's just a thermometer
and then the thermometer is unrelated to
um you know a slot machine player that's
what you have but if the slot machine's
conditioned on temperature that's what
you have the slot machine's conditioned
Upon A Taste sensor that's what you
have so it's like a toolbox for us to
take those steps and ask what if but we
can't return to the framework and ask
about whether certain factors influence
each other or not again because we can
just quickly think about examples where
they wouldn't
wouldn't that's what chapter six is
about is defining the whole generative
model not just we don't just hardcode
the
policies yeah thanks I I need to think a
more how to
how to U generalize the the policy you
know to extend the model in chapter six
uh to more General uh policy
definition okay thank you anyway for uh
clar oh
yes this
um let's look at a few of the questions
this is a great great starting
one section
10.4
there's a song
lyric and then this person has
written another verse from that
song that's a little bit
less juvenile violence in
theme
okay
anyone W to yeah yeah go ahead yeah I
just wanted to I I I need some
clarification and I think it I don't
know if it's relevant to um L's
question um
but there are states hidden states
that we attempt to infer
from um our
models that's why
understanding then there's
perception and then there's
action and one of the things that um the
themes in the book
is that action and
perception uh if I understood this
correctly are seen as one and the same
thing could you elaborate on
that
a lot of great questions I you said that
that through modeling like we we find or
we discover hidden
States a slightly more because we can't
view them we can't see them we have to
infer them right we have a microcosm of
the active agent which is that the
active agent is only getting its
sensorium the inbound and its its
actions on the outbound and it is
proposing
[Music]
latent unobserved hidden causes of
sensory phenomena to bound its surprise
so um in in this kind when we write this
kind of a model like figure
4.3 we put the hidden State down
temperature in the room we put the
observation down thermometer and then
the agent does the inference on the
hidden
state so but but we constructed the
hidden State space to be fixed or
structure learning is like when the
agent is going to be like rearranging
combinations of hidden States and and
learning the structure of the world for
itself
um action and perception are part of a
unified Unity is plural at minimum too
perception is not action Simply Now if
you look across a blanket one agent's
action becomes the
other's
perception so in that sense action and
perception are just kind of like whose
perspective are you taking from the
blanket like you
know screaming into the environment is
the action from the Yeller but then it's
the perception from the environment so
that's one sense but um action and
perception are unified in Act of
inference not by eradicating their
differences
but by understanding their complete
articulation which is the two directions
of traffic across the
blanket so it's not that you know
listening is the same as kicking your
leg it's not that perception is
action it's that they're part of a
unified cognitive framework that has a
unified imperative with free energy
minimization unified handling of
variables like this and so
on okay so having said that if you if
having said that for one
individual
agent
that when we move into really complex
systems like the social insects you work
on
who
for a complicated system like an ants
nest the system is the ants
nest can you tell me just plain English
what's this is what are the actions
examples of actions and examples of
Perceptions in that
system um sure well although the ant
colony system is like The evolutionary
replicator or or the Conan organism in
the active infrance model we made an
agent-based model with an estimate and
we used exactly the figure 4.3 type
generative model right perception was
pherone and action was
movement so broadly the the the
selection of the perception and action
of the agent is similar to any other
agent-based modeling technique if you
model the ant colony as a single
organism
that's a totally cool and valid model
there's always a plurality of models
available so modeling a single colony as
the agent maybe if you wanted to model
like a field site with just several
thousand colonies and you didn't want to
go into the estimate level of detail or
maybe the estimate level is too coar
grains and maybe you need to do an organ
specific
model these are maps not territories so
it's whatever you need to do to
take the next step on your
path not about there only being like one
ants
model right so then so then in in so as
systems so systems to me are just I
can't think of any
system that at least in the in a
phenomena that I'm familiar with where
there's anything any individual
unit because even if we go down to a
cell a cell is a system you know or if
we go down to a microb the microb is a
system and it's they're very complex
system so so it just seems to me that
there are systems and nested systems
within systems and interacting systems
and depend all kinds of systems
interacting with each other Etc
so um
so I know there are different ways of
thinking about complexity uh I think
about it right now in a very qualitative
way but it seems to me
that like for example in the ants nest
Nest you have all kinds of systems going
you have the system of the you know
maybe the um
the queen and
everything that's associated with her
reproduction then they're the systems of
all the workers do you know U keeping
the dro clean and so on and so forth so
there are so many ways that you can take
these Concepts
and and I identify markco Mark of
blankets that are relevant to different
agents within
systems and that can be then blown up to
a whole system in in my understanding
this corly yeah yeah I mean at the most
zoomed out that's also true of linear
modeling you could say well we could do
a linear aggression of the Queen's femur
versus the number of seeds per minute
per day squared you know there's no
limit to the amount of linear
aggressions um fmri analysis so this
just science and instrumentalism as a
technique
there's never any ending to how many
models can be this this is not active
specific now you said there's nested
interacting blankets or nexted an
interacting um agents also very true we
have enclosures of systems and laterally
interacting Collective Behavior but
those are expressions about the
territory you're talking about how the
colony really
is you could choose to model it in
different ways an active inference gives
us a qualif IED way to stop that
infinite
regress by saying yeah there there are
organs within the nestmate they do have
a midgut and a brain and all
this we're modeling this
level and then that's the perfect
stopping point for then a future study
to pick up there and go one level deeper
into the
blanket so it's not that one study must
make all possible models and Ma of all
detail it's
actually leading to a more principled
way of collaborating across these
different
systems that's the goal of the infer
ants and and analogously for other
systems I mean why do we have so many um
Square One models of ant
foraging but there's never like
sustained development of multiple Labs
with multiple species looking at
different foraging environments because
it's easy to make that custom model of
that one ant in that one
setting but then to generalize it to
multiple ant species or multiple
settings let alone tasks other than
foraging it's very
challenging so then the literature is
basically littered with kind of toy
models or intuition
pumps but there's never a strong
substrate to build a
real extensible model like a Linux
kernel for agent based
simulations and and those have been
tried but then those systems that try to
generalize agent based simulations
themselves get mired down in technical
details and and frictions of
accessibility but you've definitely
identified the
key aspects of what we can
explore and that's why chapter six is
provided chapter 6 doesn't say here's
how nature is organized chapter 6 says
here's how you build that generative
model and then how does chapter 10 end
build the model and get
surprised it doesn't end with great now
you've established how nature
is got it so so my
next I go with my stupid question my
next stupid question but I have to ask
it yeah because it seems like throughout
the book there's like this this in some
places is very clear and I've seen it in
other contexts where it's stated clearly
that what what
the the goal is to to take this
understanding this deep
structure based on the concepts and the
architecture of the ecosystem of active
inference whatever it looks
like you know for whomever but there's
kind of a consensus around certain ideas
that hold this conceptual framework
together but the idea is that to be able
to take that and then go to into
artificial intelligence and machine
learning and
say this stuff that we see in living
organisms this deep structure we can
translate it into a completely
artificial system and
recreate uh
actions um
by translating this deep structure into
something that works in a
machine um and then if that's the case
then I guess for me as a social
scientist is the Deep inference here
that there is really no boundary between
living and non- living
systems from a active influence
perspective
there's a lot to say on that
[Music]
um one could debate whether the
construction of a synthetic anything
synthetic chemistry synthetic drawing a
synthetic active inference agent does
constructing a synthetic anything
legitimate any Claim about the territory
just making an arts and crafts project
doesn't change the nature of the trees
and the sunset so that's one point
second point would be yeah
instrumentally if not further we have a
strong
continuity of diverse systems inert
systems sleeping systems active systems
and so on so from a
instrumental
descriptive perspective we have an
integrated modeling approach across
different kinds of systems again this
doesn't mean life and non-life are the
same exactly it means that there's a
pallet for people to say this is what I
mean by life and I made models that are
on either side of the line and this
one's in the gray Zone and someone can
say well my Line's over
here well that's just the fact of the
matter then that those people have those
different
lines yes okay thank you appreciate it
yeah these are these are let's see if we
can look at just just so that we
can okay I'll start on the
bottom okay yes thank you for this one
addressed earlier yes join everyone is
encouraged to join our broader
educational efforts and to enrich the
textbook group where we actually will do
these
things um which sections discuss is
basing computation the most effective
problem solving system for minimizing
free
energy not sure if in the book per se
they might discuss basian
optimality um other people I know
elsewhere take more like kind of first
principles here's why things should be
or ought to be
basian but suffice to say the framework
doesn't rest upon basian computation
being the most
effective this is just a framework that
we can use to describe any system now
what's the most effective to actually do
it that may or may not be doing basian
statistics but the analytical formalism
will never fail us as observers but that
doesn't mean it's the best way to build
it from the
inside it'd be helpful to provide
definitions for thermodynamics free
energy and of ACM variational free
energy throughout the book free energy
is used interchangeably with variational
free energy in this book there are
probably un less explicitly mentioned
they're only talking about variational
free energy they're never talking about
Gibbs unless they specifically called it
out and I don't think they do they're
only concerned with informational free
energy not
thermal sections on the the term of free
energy
yeah yeah definitely there's always ways
to connect it back and
um let's go
to the
strongest Alex
kefir psychophysical identity and free
energy live stream
22 this is the strongest statement or
one of the strongest statements
made that that the thermodynamic free
energy of a system directly encodes
variational free
energy so we're walking that pedagogical
line you know they're different concepts
you could link them how you want and
then kefir just runs in and says
no there the
same or there are systems for which the
thermodynamic free energy
flows do entail variational free energy
flows okay definition of
brain definitions for mind brain
Behavior yeah I mean there's there's the
author's definition and then there's our
onology and we meet every week to update
the definitions and to translate them
and to use them more coherently so
people especially are interested in
definitional questions Let's Do
It um brains and centralized nervous
systems not exactly sure what you mean
by the brain is a recent
development I
mean there going back to the last common
ancestor of vertebrates and
invertebrates there was a centralized
nervous
system and it changed in in structure
and function even in the last tens of
thousands of
years uh uh in that question it's kind
of aong the same lines of um the what's
living and what
isn't
um in the so I
guess you know I
what you're right I mean it's it's about
you as the Observer and researcher you
decide where you you know what what how
you're going to Define things what your
affordances are what is the system that
you're working with
but I when I was first reading through
the book I was just thinking are they is
this only referring to systems where you
have to have a nervous system and then
what I was talking about is that the the
human brain in the in terms of the
neurological variation that's out there
in nature it just has um you know
um very different structure very complex
structures um anyway so it's along the
line so you know do you have to have
this neurological kind of sensorium in
order for to use active in models and I
think you guys that that good
question it absolutely does not require
centralized nervous system or nervous
cells it could be a pendulum it could be
in a ner Rock on the ground it doesn't
need to be any kind of biological life
form or any kind of
anatomy
thank you yeah that's really great but
again but most of the work has arisen
from Carl friston and colleagues doing
human
neuroimaging again every single time in
chapter five that's what we emphasize
chapter 4 generative model in SS chapter
5 they go to the case and the setting
where the most work empirically has been
done which is human
Neuroscience
but there's so so many other ways to
go thank you
okay not is this a question or or what
about
this can't really see it's too
small opportunity to expand on Niche
construction I I agree with
this
okay yeah I mean the the um as everybody
you know that sequencing question we
talked about earlier like the textbook
is just one sequence and so some people
are going to say connect it more to what
has empirically been done and I want to
understand how brains work I want to
have that first person driver seat
perspective I want the stories to be
about me picking up the water me getting
out of the chair me listening to music
other people are going to say isn't it
about bigger than humans or different
than humans shouldn't we use only the
technical
mathematical aren um appeals to personal
experience possibly even
misleading everyone's right that's why
we need a bigger knowledge system that
can generate those sequenced
paths so if people want the human 101 no
math in this language they can have that
path and if somebody wants a different
language different technical level no
human examples that is also going to be
fully
consistent
um and so is is um so Chris Field's um
course on information um physics as
information
processing is that
you know in this context um trying to
connect thoughts here um is that um a
way of saying or his perspective is we
don't have to make the work so
complicated at the quantum from a
quantum physics perspective we can
actually think about active infl a
different
way
is in my and trying to get at the the
deeper structure of information process
yeah this this textbook was
written probably largely between 2018
and
2022 maybe even
2021 because it was published in March
2022 and it was centered around prison's
2019 particular physics um on graph
developed a lot the quantum free energy
principle work with Fields glazebrook
Levan Marciano at
all only was in 2022 live stream 40 so
this textbook does not include any
Quantum informatics Chris fields and
colleagues with their backgrounds in the
quantum information
Sciences made that connection between
free energy
principle and quantum
so that connection is basically
unaddressed in this
textbook only only in the most minimal
possible way hinting at the basian
mechanics so this
textbook is
um I
mean those who love the history and
philosophy of science again let us
reconvene to write these histories but
this book is in some ways like a
coda on the
[Music]
2010s of active
inference because already in the
2020s we're heading off in some new
directions and so it's kind of like an
inflection point that Consolidated a
huge amount of the past
work but now with message passing and
Julia on this side and Quantum fvp on
that side and
far more empirical applications
happening all around it's a different
environment for doing um active
inference learning and application and
for writing a textbook as we could ask
sanjiv
about so this textbook is not everything
and again just from a chapter 10
perspective in only about 200 Pages 200
very short
Pages what they've done is incredible
and that's why we can always return to
it and and um yeah even though it's only
been 18
months since it's being
released but this is
the discussion we've
had that does not conclude cohort 4 I
hope that people return um next week to
to discuss more and and um yeah update
things develop things add projects add
questions develop the
answers thank you everybody oh thank you
appreciate it see you next time see you
next time thank you Daniel bye bye
byebye